"How Bad Are Ultra-Processed Foods?"
At present, the United States
has the lowest life expectancy
of the top dozen
richest countries in the world.
We also have the greatest share
of our diet composed
of ultra-processed foods.
In fact, most of our diet.
Most of what goes
into our mouth
isn’t considered real food.
Could there be a connection?
Ultra-processed foods
are said to be troublesome
for a wide variety of reasons,
like all the packaging, etc.,
but I’m just going to discuss
the health aspects.
Based on studies encompassing
nearly ten million participants,
greater exposure
to ultra-processed food
was associated
with a higher risk
of a variety
of adverse health outcomes,
including all-cause mortality,
meaning living
a significantly shorter life.
As a reminder,
ultra-processed foods are,
"Industrial formulations
of processed food substances
that contain little
or no whole foods
and typically include
flavorings, colorings,
emulsifiers,
and other cosmetic additives."
Think Twinkies.
So, nutritionally vacuous
that you could go blind
from nutrient deficiencies
if that’s all you ate,
like this 14-year-old boy
who apparently lived
on French fries,
Pringles, white bread,
ham, and sausage.
Some of the health outcomes
make sense,
like higher ultra-processed
food consumption
being associated with more
dental cavities in kids.
That makes sense since a lot
of them are packed with sugar.
Higher ultra-processed
food consumption
is also associated
with an increased risk
of high blood pressure.
That makes sense as a lot
of them are packed with salt.
And with high blood pressures,
you can see
how there can be a higher rate
of cardiovascular events
like heart attacks and strokes.
And since
cardiovascular diseases
are our leading killers,
you can see how that could lead
to increased overall mortality.
Obesity is also a no-brainer.
A lot of ultra-processed
products
are packed with calories,
and furthermore
intentionally engineered
with hyperpalatable combinations
of fat, sugar, salt, and flavors
so you can’t just eat one,
promoting weight gain
through so-called
hedonic eating,
meaning eating for pleasure
even if you aren’t
really hungry.
I can see all that,
but why would there also
be a higher overall cancer risk
associated with ultra-processed
food consumption?
Or a higher risk of dementia?
Or a higher risk
of inflammatory bowel disease?
of irritable bowel syndrome?
And a higher risk of developing
chronic kidney disease, too?
Overall, direct associations
have been found
between exposure
to ultra-processed foods
and 70%
of the health issues
that were investigated.
A higher risk of dying
from all causes put together,
a higher risk of getting cancer,
not sleeping well,
suffering from anxiety,
depression,
and other common
mental disorders,
wheezing,
cardiovascular disease,
Crohn’s disease,
abdominal obesity,
obesity in general,
fatty liver disease,
type 2 diabetes.
So, increased risk of a variety
of chronic diseases
and mental health disorders.
And apparently
not a single study
reported an association between
ultra-processed food intake
and beneficial health outcomes.
There was never a,
"Take two Twinkies
and call me in the morning."
Given the large body of evidence
implicating ultra-processed
foods in human diseases,
and their ever-increasing
consumption around the world,
there is a pressing need
to recognize their contribution
to the global burden of disease.
All right, but wait.
These are associations.
Just because A
is correlated with B
doesn’t mean that A causes B.
Maybe B causes A.
For example,
snapshot-in-time studies show
that intake of higher
ultra-processed foods
is associated
with increased odds
of depression
or anxiety symptoms,
but individuals might turn
to ultra-processed foods
in an attempt to mitigate
stress-related anxiety.
They don’t call it
comfort food for nothin’.
Now there are
longitudinal studies
showing that greater intake
of ultra-processed foods
preceded depression,
but maybe the food was just used
to fend off bad feelings
for years before
any official diagnosis.
But reverse causation,
B causing A,
seems less plausible
when it comes
to non-mental health outcomes.
For example, it’s harder
to paint a picture
of how a heart attack
would cause people to then go on
to eat more junk food
instead of vice versa.
The other big issue when trying
to establish cause-and-effect
from observational,
correlational data
is confounding.
Maybe the reason A
is associated with B
is that some
third confounding factor, C,
is linked to both.
For example, if people
who eat more junk
tend to smoke more,
no wonder junk eaters
would be dying more,
but it would have more
to do with the cigarettes
they put in their mouth
rather than the food.
And indeed,
people consuming unhealthy diets
are also likely to smoke, drink,
and not exercise,
but we have ways to control
for these factors.
Indeed, the majority
of studies
were adjusted
for these confounders.
The most obvious
confounding factor, though,
is that highly processed foods
just tend to be more
likely to be junky crap.
The reason cakes, crullers,
candy, and cola are bad for us
may have less to do
with how much they’re processed
and more to do
with the fact
that they are cakes,
crullers, candy, and cola,
packed with sugar
and calories,
with very few nutrients.
Diets high
in ultra-processed foods
are diets high in added sugars,
saturated fat,
sodium, and calories,
displacing more
nutritious foods,
such as fruits, vegetables,
legumes, nuts, and seeds.
So, maybe ultra-processed foods
are just markers
of poor diet quality.
And indeed, the more
ultra-processed foods people eat
the more refined carbs
they’re eating,
the more sugar, saturated fat,
sodium, energy, cholesterol,
and the less fiber
in their diets.
So, where’s the mystery?
People who eat more bad foods
get more diseases.
We already knew that.
What does processing
per se have to do with it?
Because ultra-processed
category foods
are more likely
to be crappy foods,
we could use it
as a kind of heuristic
that they probably
won’t be good for us.
For example,
if you made up some rule
that you’re going to avoid
breakfast cereals
with cartoon characters on them,
you’d probably end up healthier,
but not because the graven image
of Tony the Tiger
magically hastens you
to the grave,
but rather because they’re
proxies for high sugar content.
But for the developers
of the ultra-processed concept,
"ultra-processed" was no proxy.
They claimed that
the harmful effects
of ultra-processed foods
are not fully captured
by their nutrient profile,
and even go as far to say
we should avoid
ultra-processed foods,
irrespective
of their nutrient profiles.
Whether ultra-processed diets
are detrimental to health
simply because they are
of a poor nutritional quality,
or whether the nature
and extent of processing itself
has health consequences
has been an ongoing debate.
How might we settle it?
Well, if it were the case
that the association between
ultra-processed foods
and poor health was solely
because
of the excess saturated fat,
sugar, and salt,
or just from a less healthful
dietary pattern in general,
then, if we were to adjust
for dietary quality,
the association between
ultra-processed foods
and disease should disappear.
In other words, if it was
all about the nutrients,
then people eating crappy diets
high in saturated fat,
salt, and sugar
should have high disease rates
regardless of whether they eat
more ultra-processed foods
or less of them.
And people who eat
really healthy diets
should have low rates
of disease regardless
of how many ultra-processed
foods they consume.
But that’s not the case.
The majority of the associations
between ultra-processed foods
and obesity and health problems
remain significant and unchanged
in magnitude after adjustment
for diet quality or pattern.
Meaning, even if you balance out
dietary quality,
those eating more
ultra-processed
tend to do worse.
This suggests that at least
some of the adverse consequences
of ultra-processed foods
are independent
of dietary quality,
so it’s not as though
the ultra-processed
food companies
can just reformulate
their products
to be lower in salt or sugar
and be done with it.
There appears to be something
about this class of foods
beyond the standard
nutrient profile
that contributes
to their deleterious effects.
And that’s just what
I’ll be discussing
in this extended video series
on ultra-processed foods.